– Thanks, Chris. Sorry to interrupt so
many great conversations, but this is when
I've been told to speak, so you're stuck
with me. Again, Jay Stanley with the ACLU.
I've been working for a long time for the
ACLU. I started in 2001 and I've been
dealing with a lot of tech issues since
then. Things are constantly new, so it
keeps us on our feet. And the ACLU has
always been against a national identity
system. We don't like a national ID for a
lot of reasons. For one thing, it does
take away your individual identity and it
makes it a bureaucratic artifact and it
threatens to create a system of tracking
in which government agencies and big
businesses have a unique identifier, a key
that you are stuck with and you cannot get
rid of that will track you across
different areas. If one company is
tracking you here, one government agency
is tracking you there, and somebody else
is tracking you there and they all have
their silos, that is good for privacy. A
national identity system creates a unique
identifier. And we've always… So we oppose
RealID because it basically turned our
driver's licenses into a de facto
distributed national identity system. Now,
a lot of the bad consequences that we
feared that would come from that have not
materialized. It's sort of a low-key
national identity system that we have. But
a lot of that is because it's physical.
And what we worry about with a digital
identity is that it will fully bring forth
the negative potential that Americans
across the political spectrum have always
worried about with a national ID system.
And I work on privacy issues. I have
always gotten support from the left and
from the right. I think among all the
issues the ACLU works on, it really is the
least partisan. And I think with the
national identity issue, in some ways it
is it is the left and the right against
people who aren't really thinking about it
and just marching forward. And I think
that, you know, the driver's license
started as a license to drive. You need
to, it's probably in the public interest
to license people who are drivers, but it
has become something much bigger than
that. It's become something much more
central to our society. And as it moves
online, it's going to become much, much
bigger. And that is the goal of the
digital identity proponents, of course.
So, we, I was ignoring the digital
identity issue for a while because it
seemed like nothing was going to happen.
And then in around 2001, I wrote a big
report because it seemed like this MDL
thing was really happening in the States.
We were starting to see a lot of uptake.
It was like, okay, this is real again. And
we were very concerned because it was
created by an international group, the
ISO, which included, as we know, some big
tech companies like Apple and Google and
some government agencies like DHS and
AMVA. And we don't know who else is on it.
I asked them who else was on the committee
and they refused to tell me. And also you
couldn't even see the standard without
paying thousands of dollars and it was
copyrighted. What kind of a way is that to
make public policy? Maybe that is okay for
light bulb standards or something like
that, but for something that's going to be
at the heart of the relationship between
government and the governed, that was very
dubious. And in fact, the ISO standard,
the MDL standard, reflects the interests
of who was at that table, which is the
verifiers. We're going to do everything
possible to make sure that nobody can ever
fool a verifier about their identity, but
it doesn't reflect the interests of the
holders, the people who are holding the
identity, the people whose identity has
been granted to them by the DMVs under
this thing. So, we did a report in 2001
called Identity Crisis. And then over
time, me and my colleague, who is our
technologist and others, refined our
thinking and put out a last year a set of
state legislative recommendations for
state legislators with proposed language.
It's kind of a work in progress. That's a
version 1.0. We're working on a second
version now. But the question, you know,
we've been hearing talk all day today. We
need a privacy protecting digital identity
system. We're going to have digital
identity needs to be privacy protective.
Well, when the rubber hits the road, what
does that look like? What is privacy
protective? And that's what we set out to
answer and put some meat on the bones
there. And so this report basically has 12
items that we think state legislature
should pass and basically say our state
shall not have a digital identity system
unless it has these technological
qualities and comes with these policy
envelopes and protections because you
can't do everything through technology.
Although we think you should do as much as
you can with technology because it's much
harder to change and to back out of. So
let me just I'm going to mention quickly
we're going to run through the 12 just so
you have a flavor. You can look it up if
you're interested in any of those more. I
might highlight one two, which might be
interesting that people have thought
about. And then I'm going to finish with a
couple thoughts and then I'll be done in
the next five minutes, which is how much
time I have. So one of the big features is
no phone home. If I show my driver's
license to a liquor store clerk, they look
at it. End of story. Nobody's the wiser.
If it's digital, there's the capability to
create a record. And in particular for the
issuer, the DMV, the government or the
companies that are their contractors to
see that that I've done that and what time
and at what liquor store and everywhere
else that I show my ID. Locker's offices,
etc. And it needs to be built without that
feature. There should be no phone home. We
can build it. The ISO standard allowed for
that. And that is something that we've
been working on. We think that a key
privacy feature is verifier unlinkability.
If I show my digital driver's license at
six gun shops or six liquor stores or six
doctor's offices, the companies involved
should not be able to… First of all, if I,
for example, if I have to prove I'm over
18 or I'm over 21, they should just get a
binary which a binary bit which says, yes,
no, this person's over 21 and it's
encrypted and proofed. But there shouldn't
be a unique signature or any other unique
identifier that is passed over as part of
that that can later be used to correlate
all your presentations. And there are
there are readily available cryptographic
techniques that can make that possible.
And that needs to be a part of a privacy
protecting digital identity system. New
Jersey, which may have outside of Utah the
best digital driver's license law, has
this. They say their law says, which was
just passed a couple months ago, the
system shall ensure that a digital
driver's license or non-digital license
includes techniques and methodologies that
ensure that multiple presentations of non
-unique data by a the holder cannot be
linked together by one or more verifiers.
The selective disclosure we think needs to
be mandated that basically you should have
the right to disclose the minimum amount
of data that is necessary for the
transaction. You are over 21, you are not.
You are a resident of the city without
sharing your address. Whatever the use
case may be, people should… relying
parties, verifiers shouldn't get any more
than they need for that transaction.
Here's an interesting one and I talked
about this in one of breakouts, there
shouldn't be a government's kill switch
for your identity. And I think that's
where the philosophical approach of the
government endorses your identity and
doesn't create or bestow upon you your
identity. But in bureaucratic sense,
that's what is happening in some senses.
And there is a real potential that the
government is going to have a significant
power that it has never had before. Three
steps. Step one, create a digital identity
system. Step two, allow a bunch of
dependencies to be built on that. And some
of our proposals are trying to avoid this
so that your digital identity doesn't
become the key to actually doing your
ability to do anything in life, which is a
real threat. Make it so you can't live
without the digital identity system. And
then because some governor doesn't like
your politics or whatever, pull the rug
out from those people, revoke their
digital ID and make them an unperson and
unable to do many things in society. And
that is a power a government has never had
before. But with a central digital
identity becomes a very real possibility
and danger. We think that there should be
verifier accountability. You have to
verify yourself to whoever wants you to
prove something about yourself. You should
have a verified identity of who that is
and make sure that you actually are
identifying yourself to who you think
you're identifying yourself with. That
hasn't really been implemented. We call
for an open wallet ecosystem so that
people have a choice of wallets. We think
that like forcing people to run government
code on their personal phones is bad idea.
It should not be government code. If it
is, it should certainly be open source.
But it's better to have the free market
provide lots of different wallets provided
that they meet security standards so that
people can pick whose wallet they want to
put it in whether it's Google's or
Samsung's or Apple's or maybe you know
Mozilla's or a privacy protecting group
that you have more trust in or what have
you. And we call for and one of our
biggest things is restrictions on ID
demands. The real threat here is that once
this infrastructure is created, it makes
it really frictionless to present your ID.
When you go into websites, unless they
really need you to approve ID, they do not
ask you to approve your ID. They're not
going to like make you get a camera and go
in different angles and show your ID. It's
too big an ask. They'll scare away
customers and they know that. But if they
can send you a pop-up says click here to
send us your digital driver's license,
they will. They'll have a bunch of
incentives to do it for advertising and to
make sure you know who you are as cookies
go away potentially. for security and
forensics. And so the real danger is that
we wake up one day, say, oh, you want to
watch this YouTube video? Well, just click
here to send us your digital driver's
license. You click no. Sorry, we can't. It
could be used for surveillance pricing
where companies set their prices for you
based on who you are and everything they
know about you rather than offering the
same price to everybody else. And there's
a lot of abuses there. So let me just… I'm
running out of time rapidly. Let me just
finish up by saying that that the really
important thing here is that legislators
decide. We have our 12 things that we
think are important parts of privacy.
Maybe some people disagree with we're
going to have disagreements over some of
those and the details and they're complex.
But I think we should all agree that it
should be part of the political process.
It should be legislators who are making
these value judgments. We obviously don't
want legislators getting the nuts and
bolts of technology, but this should be
back in the hands of the legislature. It
should not be in the hands of secret
international committee, China and Russia.
or I'm part of the overseeing committee of
the smaller committee. It should not be
technologists in the DMV who are just been
told to implement it or get to make the
decisions in the dark of night. It should
not be unaccountable private organizations
like AMVA. No shade on AMVA, but they came
out of the old world where it's about
licensing digital driver's licenses. And
this is much, much bigger than that. I'm
sorry, licensing your ability to drive.
This is much bigger than that. And it's,
it can't be left to a private organization
that asserts copyrights in its policy
documents. It won't let people publish
them. let alone not being subject to the
privacy action FOIA and so forth, checks
and balances on government. And it should
not be the TSA. The TSA right now, because
of RealID, has the power to shape what our
digital identity system looks like. It
should be legislators and the political
community. And one of the things that's
really fantastic about SEDI, and I think
that there's a bunch of traps and there
are questions and I don't know what it'll
look like as it evolves and what the ACLU
you will think of it, but I think it's
fantastic that these decisions have moved
from people who are not involved and are
not going to be affected to the political
level, which is where it belongs. Thank
you.